Alright, so today's דף *daf* יח *Yud-Chet*, we pick up at the
bottom of or, unfortunately, at the top of the middle of יז
*Yud-Zayin* עמוד ב *Amud Bet*.
We pick up
with... okay, one minute... אמר רבי יוחנן Yochanan. *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, the
first wide line of יז *Yud-Zayin* עמוד ב *Amud Bet*, about a
third from the top. אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, says רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, גדולה תשובה teshuva. שמקרעת גזר דינו של אדם *Gedola
teshuva she-mekara'at
gzar dino shel adam*. Greatest תשובה teshuvah *teshuva*—so now we're back to
the sort of dialectic between the idea of a גזר דין Gezar
din, *gzar din* and then the idea of תפילה tefilla. *tefilla* and
תשובה teshuvah *teshuva* that allows for a constant reassessment. So, greatest תשובה
teshuvah *teshuva* that tears up the גזר דין Gezar din. *gzar din*,
the, you know, the sort of like the document in which your,
in which your judgment has been written, של אדם *shel adam*, שנאמר
she-ne'emar: *she-ne'emar*: השמן לב העם הזה ואזניו הכבד ועיניו השע פן יראה
בעיניו ובאזניו ישמע ולבבו יבין ושב ורפא לו *Hishmen lev ha-am ha-zeh
ve-oznav hachbed ve-einav hasha pen yireh ve-einav u-ve-oznav yishma u-levavo yavin va-shav
ve-rafa lo*. So, you know, the heart of this people has become
fat and their ears heavy and their eyes blind, lest they see
with their eyes and their ears hear and their heart understand, and
they will do תשובה teshuvah. *teshuva* and then they'll be healed. So
you see that תשובה teshuvah, *teshuva* works even after גזר דין gezar
din. *gzar din*. So the obvious question is, אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי *Amlei Rav Papa L'Abaye*, ודילמא לפני גזר דין gezar din *ve-dilma
lifnei gzar din*? Who told you it was after גזר דין gzar
din *gzar din*? Maybe that was before גזר דין gzar din. *gzar
din*? אמר ליה *Amar lei*, ורפא לו כתיב *ve-rafa lo ktiv*—it says
you'll be healed. איזהו דבר שצריך רפואה *Eizehu davar she-tzarich refua*? Why
do you need healing? הוי אומר זה גזר דין gzar din *Hevei
omer zeh gzar din*. It must be that there was already an
edict against you, there was something that was bad that now needs
healing. Okay, why wouldn't it say healing in terms of your own,
you know, your own personhood and yourself as the, you know, and
your own deeds? But okay.
So, מיתיבי *Meitivei*, they asked on this. So now we're going to
deal with this question whether תשובה teshuvah *teshuva* works after גזר דין
gzar din *gzar din*. השב בין ראש השנה Rosh Hashana ליום הכיפורים
מוחלין לו *Hashav bein Rosh Hashanah l'Yom ha-Kippurim mochalin lo*. So if
you do תשובה *teshuva* between ראש השנה Rosh Hashana? *Rosh Hashanah* and
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, it'll be forgiven to you. לא
Lo, שב בין תחיים *Lo shav bein tichayim*—if you don't do תשובה
*teshuva* between ראש השנה Rosh Hashana *Rosh Hashanah* and יום כיפור Yom
Kippur, *Yom Kippur*—אפילו הביא כל אילי נביות שבעולם אין מוחלין לו *afilu
heivi kol eilei nevayot she-ba'olam ein mochalin lo*,
even if you bring all like the, you know, rams for sacrifices,
all these fat rams in the world, אין מוחלין לו *ein mochalin
lo*, it won't be forgiven to you. So you see that after
the גזר דין gzar din *gzar din*, it won't be forgiven, you
only have your chance until יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. That's
the context. לא קשיא *Lo kashya*, it's not difficult. הא ביחיד הא
בציבור *Ha b'yachid ha b'tzibur*. Difference whether it's a יחיד yachid. *yachid*
or ציבור tzibur. *tzibur*. So now we're modifying ourselves. We're saying that
תשובה *teshuva* works after גזר דין gzar din *gzar din* only for
a ציבור tzibur. *tzibur*. Alright, well that's pretty radically modified. That means
that every individual after יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* has no
chance of reversing any decisions that were made by יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. Unless he's on his own.
Well, right. So anyway, let's keep on going. מיתיבי *Meitivei*, they asked
on this. עיני ה' אלהיך בה *Einei Hashem Elokecha bah*. The eyes
of God are on it, the land of Israel, from the beginning
of the year to the end of the year. עתים לטובה ועתים
לרעה *Eitin l'tova v'eitin l'ra'a*. Sometimes God will be inspecting it later
in the year for good, sometimes for bad. עתים לטובה כיצד *Eitin
l'tova keitzad*? How is it for good? הרי שהיו ישראל רשעים resha'im
גמורים בראש השנה *Harei she-hayu Yisrael resha'im gmurim b'Rosh Hashanah*. Let's say
they were completely wicked on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*. ופסקו
להם גשמים מועטים *V'pasku lahem gshamim mu'atim*. And it was decided there
would only be a small amount of rain. By the way, notice
here the connection of the גזר דין gzar din *gzar din* of
rain on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, it goes back to
some of the tensions in that משנה Mishnah *mishna* about rain as
opposed to, you know, and when is the rain as opposed to,
and when is the person, etc. Anyway, it was decreed that they
would only have a small amount of rain on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*. ולסוף חזרו בהן *U-lesof chazru bahen*, and then they
did תשובה *teshuva*—funny, חזרו *chazru*, they didn't say עשו תשובה *asu teshuva*,
they reversed themselves, they went back to their evil ways—להוסיף עליהם אי
אפשר *l'hosif aleihem i efshar*, you can't add to them, שכבר נגזרה
גזירה *she-kvar nigzera gzeira*, the גזירה *gzeira* was already decreed. אלא ella,
הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu מורידם בזמנם *Ela Hakadosh Baruch Hu
moridam bizmanan*. God will bring the rain, but He'll bring it at
the exact perfect time. So it'll be a small amount, but it'll
be at the right time. על הארץ הצריכה להן *al ha-aretz ha-tzricha
lahen*, and exactly on the lands that need them. So even a
small amount, if it's at exactly place, it'll, it'll be for good.
So the גזירה *gzeira*'s true, and in the end, there's a, you
know, the תשובה *teshuva* has its effect.
So the תשובה *teshuva*'s after יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*?
Yeah, the תשובה *teshuva* is after יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*.
All right, הכל לפי הארץ *Hakol l'fi ha-aretz*.
Everything according to what is exactly needed for the land. עתים לרעה
כיצד *Eitin l'ra'a keitzad*? Sometimes it'll be for bad. How? הרי שהיו
ישראל צדיקים tzadikim גמורים בראש השנה *Harei she-hayu Yisrael tzaddikim gmurim b'Rosh
Hashanah*. They were totally צדיקים tzadikim *tzaddikim*, ופסקו להם גשמים מרובים *v'pasku
lahem gshamim merubim*, and it was decreed that they would have a
lot of rain. ולסוף חזרו בהן *U-lesof chazru bahen*. So then they
did תשובה *teshuva*—funny, חזרו *chazru*, they didn't say עשו תשובה *asu teshuva*,
they reversed themselves, they went back to their evil ways. לפחות מהם
אי אפשר *L'fachot meihem i efshar*, you can't give them less than
what was decreed, שכבר נגזרה גזירה *she-kvar nigzera gzeira*, the גזירה *gzeira*
was already decreed. אלא הקדוש ברוך הוא מורידם שלא בזמנם *Ela Hakadosh
Baruch Hu moridam she-lo bizmanan*, brings it in the bad time when
rain isn't good for the crops, על ארץ שאינה צריכה להן *al
aretz she-eina tzricha lahen*, on the land that does not need them.
So anyway, the גזירה *gzeira*'s true and the תשובה *teshuva* or the
reversal actually, interesting of deeds is effective. So again, playing between the
idea of a גזר דין gzar din. *gzar din* and a constant
reevaluation of your deeds and what you are deserving. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, לטובה מיהא ליקרע לגזר דיניהם ולוסיף להו *L'tova miha
likra l'gzar dineihem v'losif lehu*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I don't get it though, that's
sort of saying we're going to play within the system. But according
to you, תשובה *teshuva* can really tear up the גזר דין gzar
din *gzar din*, you don't even have to worry about the early.
your decree. So why didn't if in that scenario, why didn't it
just say that God tears up the גזר דין? gzar din. So
the גמרא Gemara says שאני התם דאפשר בהכי. shani hatam de'efshar behachi.
No, as long as you can work within the system we'll work
with the system. Okay, so there, but אי הכי נמי, ee hachi
nami, if it required a tearing up of the גזר דין, gzar
din it would tear up of the גזר דין. gzar din Okay,
תא שמע, tashma, of course it's from the ציבור. tzibur. Of course
it's funny like, the whole thing that we read by יונה Yonah
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur? is very
much God reverses His decree is that idea. I mean, some of
that imagery right about God making a decree and reversing it and
so on. I mean, you get some of that in יונה. Yonah.
Now so that was a ציבור. tzibur. תא שמע, tashma, okay, יורדי
הים באניות, yordeiy hayam be'oniyot, so this is the פסוקים psukim in
תהלים Tehillim about actually this serves as the basis for the
קרבן תודה Korban Toda because it gives scenarios where people see God's
saving hand and come back and give thanks. So יורדי הים באניות
yordeiy hayam be'oniyot those who go down to the sea in the
ships, עושי מלאכה במים רבים osei melacha bemayim rabim that they do
their work in the great waters, המה ראו מעשי ה' heima ra'u
ma'asei Hashem they saw the great, they see the great deeds of
God.
ויאמר ויעמד רוח סערה ותרומם גליו, vayomar vaya'amod ruach se'ara vateromeim galav,
יחוגו וינועו כשיכור. yachogu veyanu'u kashikor. So a great wind comes up
in the sea and the waves get raised very high and they
sway back and forth like the drunk. ויצעקו אל ה' בצר להם
vayitz'aku el Hashem batzar lahem they call out to God when it
is in their anguish. יודו לה' חסדו yodu l'Hashem chasdo and then
God saves them, יודו לה' חסדו yodu l'Hashem chasdo they give thanks
to God for His kindness, for His greatness. Okay, so עשה להן
סימניות כאכין ורקין שבתורה. aseh lahen simaniyot k'achin ve'rachin she'baTorah. Now if
you look at where that appears in תנ"ך, Tanakh, I should have
brought a תנ"ך Tanakh but I did not. It's right here. Okay,
over there? Let's see if it replicates visually what it looks like
because there where that appears in תנ"ך Tanakh there are little as
the גמרא Gemara says little special letters. רש"י Rashi has it
like the ויהי בנסע. vayehi binsoa. Right, which is exactly what it
looks like, it's something that רש"י Rashi actually says
כזה kazei because it's exactly that.
Yeah, here. I don't know if people can see.
This passage in תהלים, Tehillim, do you see?
Can you see here? It's the very beginning.
Can
you see the little נונים nuns here, the upside down נונים nuns
at the beginning of the פסוקים? psukim? You'll trust me, you can
pass it around. Okay, so all the things that speak about these
people seeing the great things of God in the beginning of each
פסוק pasuk right there in the upper right hand corner you see
the little נון. nun. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says you can
pass it to the other side. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
okay right. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says, where are we? אכין
ורקין. achin ve'rachin. Wait a minute, עשה להן סימניות, aseh lahen simaniyot,
it made these little signs in the beginning of the פסוקים, psukim,
כאכין ורקין שבתורה, k'achin ve'rachin she'baTorah, those signs show a certain sense
of like the word אך ach or רק, rak, like a little
sense of that it's there's a reservation there. It's not complete. What
does that mean? It means לומר לך lomar lekha to tell you,
צעקו קודם גזר דין tza'aku kodem gezar din so here they are
and the boat's about to be overturned and it says they call
out to God and God answers them, but with those little סימנים
simanim to tell you but not always, like an asterisk sort of
like the גמרא Gemara says.
It's like a big promise like here's this amazing thing but there's
a little asterisk. What does the asterisk mean? The asterisk means that
only if they called out to God before גזר דין. gzar din
צעקו קודם גזר דין נענין tza'aku kodem gezar din na'anin then they'll
be answered. צעקו לאחר גזר דין tza'aku le'achar gezar din if they
called out after גזר דין gzar din אינן נענין einan na'anin they
will not be answered. What? יחיד וציבור. yeichid v'tzibur. Yeah, well, I
don't know if it's everybody on the ship. So let's take a
look. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. הני נמי כיחידים דמו.
hani nami keyichidim dami. Okay, so maybe you got a ship full
of people but they're not a ציבור. tzibur So that's not a
proof. So now we're sort of re-affirming this idea that it works
after גמר דין gmar din but only for a ציבור. tzibur תא
שמע, tashma, no let's look at תא שמע, tashma, שאלה בלוריא הגיורת,
sha'ala Bluriya hagioret, בלוריא Bluriya the גיורת gioret asked רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, don't you see, כתיב בתורתכם ktiv be'Torat'chem it says in
your תורה. Torah. Okay, interesting. So if you take a look in
the שאילתות She'iltot where it repeats this
story it doesn't have the word בתורתכם be'Torat'chem because בתורתכם be'Torat'chem is
usually said when a non-Jew is challenging the rabbis but here she's
a גיורת. gioret. Okay, maybe she asked it before she converted. Anyway
let's take a look. אשר לא ישא פנים, asher lo yisa panim,
God does not show favor, וכתיב uchtiv but then the פסוק pasuk
says ישא ה' פניו אליך, yisa Hashem panav eilecha, God will lift
His countenance to you. Now of course that's really not a contradiction
because as the תוספות Tosfot says that אשר לא ישא פנים asher
lo yisa panim means that God doesn't show favor doesn't play
favorites because somebody is rich or of a status, doesn't get a
partial treatment. And God ישא ה' פניו אליך yisa Hashem panav eilecha
means that God shows a good a positive countenance towards you, God
is favorable towards you. But anyway let's take a look, it asks
as a contradiction. נתפל לה רבי יוסי הכהן. nitpal lah Rabbi Yosei
HaKohen. רבי יוסי הכהן Rabbi Yosei HaKohen was given over to answer
her. He said to her, he said to her, אמשול לך משל,
emshol lakh mashal, let me give you an example. למה הדבר דומה
לאדם שנושה בחברו מנה, lemah hadavar domeh le'adam shenosheh bechavero maneh, excuse
me,
a person who is owed by his friend a מנה. maneh. who
has lent his friend a hundred dollars. וקבע לו זמן בפני המלך,
ve-kava lo zman bifnei ha-melech,
and he said and they went in front of the king and
the guy and said you're going to pay me by this date.
ונשבע לו בחיי המלך, ve-nishba lo be-chayei ha-melech, and he the guy
who owed the money took an oath in the life of the
king that he would pay him. הגיע זמן ולא פרע, hegia zman
ve-lo para, and the time came and the guy didn't pay. בא
לפייס את המלך, ba le-fayes et ha-melech, so the debtor went to
the king because he basically had now, you know, it was a
sin against the king not just against the creditor. ואמר לו, ve-amar
lo, and the king said to him, עלבוני מחול לך, elboni machul
lach, my offense I will be מוחל mocheil to you. לך ופייס
את חברך, lech u-fayes et chaveircha, you have to go now appease
your friend because he's the one that you also took, you know,
did not pay up the money to. הכא נמי, hacha nami, here
too, כאן בין אדם למקום כאן בין אדם לחברו, kan bein adam
la-makom kan bein adam la-chavero,
it depends when between people or between a person and God. When
it's between you and God, ישא ה' פניו אליך, yisa Hashem panav
eleicha, so the word of נושא nosei also is connected with נושא
עון, nosei avon, right? So God will forgive you. But אשר לא
ישא פנים, asher lo yisa fanim, when will God not forgive you?
When it is you are sinning against another person and then as
long as you have not made good with the other person God
will not forgive you. עד שבא רבי עקיבא ולימד, ad she-ba Rabbi
Akiva ve-limed,
that's how he read the verses. Until רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva came
and said, פסוק זה וכתוב אחר, pasuk zeh ve-katuv acher, כאן קודם
גזר דין כאן לאחר גזר דין. kan kodem gzar din kan le-achar
gzar din. The difference is before גזר דין gezar din and after
גזר דין. gezar din. Before גזר דין gezar din. God will forgive
you, after גזר דין gezar din God will not forgive you.
So the גמרא Gemara says, oh, you see, after גזר דין gezar
din no forgiveness. Same answer, הכא נמי ביחיד, hacha nami be-yachid, here
too we're talking about an individual. Okay, so now we have had
a lot of contradictions and we've resolved them by saying גזר דין
gezar din is torn up after is could be torn up for
a ציבור tzibur. and not for a יחיד. yachid So now the
גמרא's Gemara going to not be satisfied with that because that again
pretty much means that as a יחיד yachid you're stuck. So the
גמרא Gemara says, וגזר דין דיחיד תנאי היא,
ve-gzar
din
de-yachid tannai hi, but at the end of the day the גזר
דין gezar din of the יחיד yachid is a תנאי היא tannai
hi whether that will be torn up after גזר דין. gezar din.
דתניא, de-tanya, taught in a ברייתא, braita, היה רבי מאיר אומר, haya
Rabbi Meir omer, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say, שנים שעלו
למטה, shnayim she-alu le-mita, two people went into the bed, and this
means that two people got sick, you know, were taken to the
hospital. וחוליין שוה, ve-cholyan shaveh,
and they had the same illness. וכן שנים שעלו לגרדום, ve-chen shnayim
she-alu le-gardom,
or two people were brought to the be judged, you know, by
the to be judged for a capital crime. לידון, li-don, so the
גרדום gardom was some the place where you know they were people
were judged for very for capital crime. From Latin, what's it from
Latin word meaning what?
It means step, it applies to the the way that the Romans
would execute people.
Okay, like a
gallows. ודמם שוה, ve-damam shaveh, and they both have you know they
both have the same judgment passed against them. They're both the you
know they're both being taken in for murder or something. זה ירד
וזה לא ירד, zeh yarad ve-zeh lo yarad, but then what happens?
The outcomes are different. One guy gets off the bed, one guy
comes home from the hospital, and the other guy died. זה ניצל
וזה לא ניצל, zeh nitzal ve-zeh lo nitzal, one guy gets freed
from the from the court and the other guy didn't and got
executed. מפני מה זה ירד וזה לא ירד זה ניצל וזה לא
ניצל? mipnei ma zeh yarad ve-zeh lo yarad zeh nitzal ve-zeh lo
nitzal? How did it be that the outcomes are different? It must
be זה התפלל ונענה וזה התפלל ולא נענה. zeh hitpalel ve-ne'eneh ve-zeh
hitpalel ve-lo ne'eneh. The one prayed and was answered and one prayed
and wasn't answered. Okay, so that's the difference, one prayed. מפני מה,
mipnei ma, I'm sorry, they both prayed,
right? So מפני מה זה נענה וזה לא נענה? mipnei ma zeh
ne'eneh ve-zeh lo ne'eneh? Why was one answered and one not answered?
זה התפלל תפילה שלימה נענה וזה לא התפלל
תפילה שלימה לא נענה. zeh hitpalel tefilla shleima ne'eneh ve-zeh lo hitpalel
tefilla shleima lo ne'eneh. One prayed a true prayer, a full prayer,
and the other one was not a full prayer. Okay, so again
here's obviously the rabbi's trying to explain, you know, why things happen
in the world and what's the logical connection between those and שכר
ועונש sachar va-onesh and deeds and, you know, just trying to explain
God's hand in natural events, so attributing here to the question about
how good was your תפילה. tefilla. You know, but of course these
are the big problems. You know, it's like the גמרא Gemara we
said yesterday about like on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah everything gets decided,
you know, צדיקים tzaddikim, will die and רשעים resha'im will live, excuse
me, that was Freudian, צדיקים will live and רשעים resha'im, will die,
and then the world doesn't exactly work out that way. So here
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is trying to explain it based on how
good was your תפילה. tefilla, רבי אלעזר אמר, Rabbi Elazar amar, רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar had a different answer. כאן קודם גזר דין כאן
לאחר גזר דין. kan kodem gzar din kan le-achar gzar din. Maybe
one of them, they're both the same things were happening here on
the earth, but one of them there was already had been a
גזר דין gezar din for him, the other up in heaven there
had not been a גזר דין. gezar din, Okay, so again that
would reinforce the idea that after גזר דין gezar din. you're stuck.
So he's talking about two different time frames?
No, maybe you know I don't know who knows what happens to
the person on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah We don't know what happens
up in heaven. And now it is the middle of the year,
they're both they both went to the hospital, but on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah. one of them had a גזר דין gezar din for
מיתה mita and the other didn't. So there see the גזר דין
gezar din cannot be reversed. רבי יצחק אמר, Rabbi Yitzchak amar, יפה
צעקה לאדם בין קודם גזר דין בין לאחר גזר דין. yafa tze'aka
la-adam bein kodem gzar din bein le-achar gzar din. So here's the
point we were looking for, which is finally an opinion that says
that even after גזר דין gezar din, and even for an individual
there can always be a reversal. Crying out, notice he says crying
out because that was the context of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, תפילה,
tefillah? interestingly not תשובה. Crying out is good for a person, presumably
תשובה would also be good, but crying out is good for a
person whether before גזר דין gezar din or after גזר דין. gezar
din Okay, so meaning he didn't explain the idea of why one
survived and one didn't, but, you know, maybe that's, but he does
understood the idea that you can always reverse the גזר דין. gezar
din So now the גמרא Gemara says, וגזר דין דציבור מי מיקרע?
V'gezar din d'tzibur mi mikra? So on the one hand we had
an opinion that says that even the גזר דין gezar din. of
a יחיד yachid could be torn up. Now we're going to go
to the opposite extreme. Who says that a גזר דין Gzar Din.
of a ציבור tzibur could be torn up? והכתיב, V'ha k'tiv, one
verse says, כבסי מרעה לבך, Kabb'si me'ra'ah libbech, cleanse your heart from
evil, וכתיב uch'tiv and the other verse says, אם תכבסי בנתר ותרבי
לך בורית נכתם עונך לפני, Im t'khabb'si baneter v'tarbi lach borit nikhtam
avonech l'fanai, if you will cleanse yourself with lye and have much
soap, nevertheless your sin is your sin is always stained before me.
So you see you can't cleanse the sin. ומה לאו U'ma lav
and that was ירמיה Yirmiyahu talking to the entire
people. So ומה לאו? U'ma lav? Presumably the reconciliation is that what
is talking before גזר דין Gzar Din, the other after. And you
see that after גזר דין Gzar Din you can never fully cleanse
it, even for a ציבור. tzibur. גמרא Gemara says, לא, no. אידי
ואידי לאחר גזר דין. Idi v'idi l'achar gezar din. They're both after
גזר דין. Gzar Din And so what does it mean you can't
cleanse it? If we've been insisting that at least for a ציבור
tzibur definitely there's a reversal. לא קשיא כאן בגזר דין שיש עמו
שבועה כאן בגזר דין שאין עמו שבועה. Lo kashya, kan b'gezar din
she'yesh immo shevu'ah, kan b'gezar din she'ein immo shevu'ah.
So now like all these different stages, it's quite fascinating again, right?
The גמרא Gemara. has an idea of דין din and a גמר
דין. gmar din. But wait, what about the idea of עד שלא
נחתם גזר דין? ad she'lo nechtam gezar din? What about the idea
of שבועה? shevu'ah? What about the idea of תפילה? Okay, so we
have a גזר דין din plus we've got תשובה that can always
work to reverse that. And then the question of יחיד yachid. and
ציבור. tzibur. But then we have these other פסוקים p'sukim that sound
like you can't reverse it. So now we're going to create yet
another hierarchy, which is not there's a normal גזר דין, din there's
כתיבה k'tivah and there's חתימה, chatimah, it's written on יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, it's נחתם. nechtam. That's a גזר דין. din That however can
still be reversed. But then there's this other hierarchy which is a
גזר דין with a שבועה, shevu'ah, when God takes an oath that
this is the way it's going to remain. Then that can't be
reversed. Okay? דאמר שמואל בר אמי אמר רב שמואל בר אמי ואמרי
לה אמר רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן מנין לגזר דין
שיש עמו שבועה שאינו נקרע?
D'amar Shmuel bar Ami, amar Rav Shmuel bar Ami, v'amri lah amar
Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan, minayin l'gezar din she'yesh immo
shevu'ah she'eino nikra?
How do we know a גזר דין that has a שבועה shevu'ah
that that won't be torn up even for a ציבור tzibur. presumably?
שנאמר ולכן נשבעתי לבית עלי אם יתכפר עון בית עלי בזבח ובמנחה.
Shene'emar, ul'khen nishba'ti l'veit Eli im yitkapper avon beit Eli b'zevach u'v'minchah.
So I have taken an oath that it will not be atoned
for. That's for an individual. Right. So I don't exactly get it.
Number one, it's for an individual. Number two is, okay, God made
a שבועה. shevu'ah. How do you know that it means that God,
how what, why לבית עלי? l'veit Eli? It's not a ציבור. tzibur,
I don't know, I would agree with Michael. I don't think that
that's normally what constitutes a ציבור. tzibbur But okay. But I don't
know, all you see there is that there was a שבועה. shevu'ah.
I don't know how you see that that means that it won't
ever be written up. Of course that's the whole idea of the
שבועה, shevu'ah, that this is the way it will remain. But I
don't see exactly what you see from the פסוק. pasuk. Anyway, okay,
so what's also fascinating is we introduce an idea of a כתיבה
k'tivah and a חתימה chatimah and a גזר דין, but we don't
let it lay that way. We think about the fact that it
could be torn up and maybe certainly for a ציבור, tzibbur maybe
for a יחיד. yachid. Now we've introduced the idea of a שבועה
shevu'ah and said that a שבועה shevu'ah with a שבועה shevu'ah it
can't be torn up. But now look what we're going to do.
We're not going to let that sit either. So let's see the
next statement. גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says
רבא, Rava, בזבח ובמנחה אינו מתכפר. B'zevach u'v'minchah eino mitkapper. The sin
won't be atoned for for by a sacrifice or by a grain
offering, אבל מתכפר בתורה, aval mitkapper b'Torah, it can be atoned for
by תורה. Torah. So it's not really violating the שבועה. shevu'ah. It's
just playing like the loopholes as it were, okay? So fine, that's
the way it won't be atoned, but maybe there's still a way
it could be atoned for. אביי אמר בזבח ובמנחה אינו מתכפר אבל
מתכפר בתורה ובגמילות חסדים. Abaye amar b'zevach u'v'minchah eino mitkapper aval mitkapper
b'Torah u'v'gemilut chasadim. Atone with גמילות חסדים. gemilut chasadim. Now this is
a very famous גמרא. Gemara. Now there's a question whether the first
statement was רבא Rava or רבה. Rabbah. Most people have the first
statement being רבה Rabbah and it's consistent now with the next statement.
רבה ואביי מדבית עלי קאתו. Rabbah v'Abaye mi'devei Eli ka'atu. רבה Rabbah
and אביי Abaye were both descendants of בית עלי. Beit Eli. So
the reason they say it can't be רבא Rava is because is
because עלי Eli was obviously a כהן kohen and רבא Rava we
know was not a כהן, kohen, although רש"י Rashi says maybe his
mother, you know maybe through his mother's side he was descended of
בית עלי, Beit Eli, which would be interesting if that would be
included in the curse, right? Even the mother, even the women descendants.
Okay, but we'll do with רבה. Rabbah. רבה Rabbah and אביי Abaye
from were בית עלי. Beit Eli. רבה דעסק בתורה חיה ארבעין שנין.
Rabbah d'asak b'Torah chaya arba'in shanin. רבה Rabbah who learned תורה Torah
lived for forty years, because that was some degree of a כפרה
kapparah for the sin. We'll see that if you don't have a
כפרה kapparah for the sin of בית עלי Beit Eli you die
much you even younger than that, much younger. אביי דעסק בתורה ובגמילות
חסדים, Abaye d'asak b'Torah u'v'gemilut chasadim, and אביי Abaye who said that
it's atoned for with תורה Torah and גמילות חסדים gemilut chasadim and
he in his own life was עוסק osek in תורה Torah and
גמילות חסדים, gemilut chasadim, חיה שיתין שנין. chaya shitin shanin. He lived
even longer, he lived sixty years. If you take a look תוספות
Tosafot says at the end of this תוספות, Tosafot, one minute he
says like this, and תוספות רבה, Tosafot Rabbah, it's
near the bottom, it's the line that starts with the word דהכא,
dehacha, it's about six lines before the תוספות Tosafot ends. He says
דהכא משמע דרבה לא היה לו זכות דגמילות חסדים והאמרינן בפרק
חלק אמרי ליה אביי לרבה בר
מר התורה הגמילות חסדים
de-hacha mashma di-Rabbah lo haya lo zechus
de-Gemilas Chasadim v’ha-amrinan
b’perek Chelek amlei Abaye l’Rabbah bar Mar
ha-Torah ha-Gemilas Chasadim and that אביי Abaye himself says to Rabbah, but
the master has in his hands תורה Torah and גמילות חסדים. Gemilas
Chasadim. ומשני מכל מקום אביי עסיק טפי מיניה. u-meshani mikol makom Abaye
asik tifei minei. Alright, nevertheless, אביי Abaye still did it was more
עסיק oseik in it, right? So that's a question like a lot
of people, you know, fine, they do some good deeds, they have
גמילות חסדים, Gemilas Chasadim, but are you עסיק oseik in גמילות חסדים?
Gemilas Chasadim? Like how much do you make it like a major
commitment and a major part of what your, you know, emphasis and
your religious pursuits are? So אביי Abaye really emphasized not just תורה
Torah but also doing good in the world and גמילות חסדים, Gemilas
Chasadim, and it had this much much more efficacious effect. Yes. And
yet we rule against אביי Abaye almost all the time. This is
not a halachic debate, but alright. So it's a very powerful statement,
you know, about what it means just to be this is from
within the rabbis, you know, just to be in the world like
in the little בית מדרש Beis Medrash and just, you know, just
to be staying within the rabbinic circle and learning תורה Torah as
opposed to that obligation and that mandate to be עסיק oseik in
גמילות חסדים Gemilas Chasadim and the impact that it had. Yes. What
do you make in that same תוספות? Tosfos? Apparently Rabbah had a
theological view that במזלא. be-mazla. Yeah, that's like a huge. Now you
understand why I skipped that. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara? says
like this. תא שמע, Ta shema, we'll do that one we learned
that גמרא. Gemara Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. You mean to say
we moved on to the other גמרא? Gemara No, I won't, that's
not the topic here, that's the topic over there. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our
rabbis taught, 60 years is important because the גמרא Gemara says that,
right, that if you die, you know, that at anybody who dies
under 60 is considered still
within
the
edict
of
like
כרת.
kares.
That the idea of כרת, kares, let's
put
it this way,
כרת
kares
in
the
גמרא
Gemara
means
that
somebody
will
die, the
way
the
גמרא Gemara understands,
under 60.
It
doesn't
mean that
every, I don't think it's supposed to mean that anybody who dies
under 60 is understood to be under that decree, but nevertheless, the
idea that even אביי Abaye did not, you know, was only up
to 60 years, because still, still was the curse, you know, was
still in effect. He only, he only pushed it off to a
certain degree, you know, he only atoned for it to a certain
degree. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught: משפחה אחת היתה בירושלים
שהיו מתיה מתים בני י"ח שנה. mishpacha achas haysa bi-Yerushalayim she-hayu meseha
mesim bnei yud ches shanah. There was a certain family in ירושלים
Yerushalayim that everybody used to die in 18 years. באו והודיעו את
רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. bau ve-hodi'u es Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. They
told רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai. אמר להם, amar
lahem, he said to them: שמא ממשפחת עלי אתם? shema mi-mishpachas Eli
atem? Maybe you're from the house of עלי? Eli? דכתיב ביה: de-chsiv
beih: וכל מרבית ביתך ימותו אנשים. ve-chol marbis beischa yamusun anashim. All
of the multitudes of your house will die as men while they're
still like young men. לכו ועסקו בתורה וחיו. lechu ve-isku ba-Torah va-chyu.
Go learn תורה Torah and you will live. הלכו ועסקו בתורה וחיו.
halchu ve-isku ba-Torah va-chyu. They went and they learned תורה Torah and
they lived. והיו קורין אותם משפחת יוחנן על שמו. ve-hayu korin osam
mishpachas Yochanan al shemo. They called it the family of יוחנן. Of
course, it's interesting, he said "learn תורה", Torah he didn't say "תורה
Torah and גמילות חסדים". Gemilas Chasadim Okay, one also fine. You know,
it's interesting also that the whole issue of, you know, the rabbinic
role replacing the role of the כהנים. Kohanim. So the, as so
the, it might be the קרבנות korbanos have lost their efficacy, but
תורה, Torah, which is the replacement of the קרבנות, korbanos, right, in
the post-חורבן Churban period, has not lost its efficacy. And also the
whole idea about, you know, that the problem of בית עלי Beis
Eli was that it was the power that led to the abuse,
you know, sort of, so the, you know, what happens when you
empower a particular religious class and the abuse that it leads to.
So presumably that's also has to do with the importance of גמילות
חסדים, Gemilas Chasadim, the idea that if a life of תורה Torah
translates also into גמילות חסדים, Gemilas Chasadim, then that's really the atonement
for the sin of בית עלי. Beis Eli. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב שמואל בר איניא משמיה דרב. amar Rav
Shmuel bar Inya mishmei de-Rav. So basically what have we said? There's
a גזר דין with a שבועה shvuah that can't be torn up,
but maybe there can be some loopholes, and then there's a normal
גזר דין which could be torn up for a ציבור tzibbur and
maybe even for a יחיד. yachid Okay. אמר רב שמואל בר איניא
משמיה דרב: amar Rav Shmuel bar Inya mishmei de-Rav: מנין לגזר דין
של ציבור שאינו נחתם? minayin le-gezar din shel tzibbur she-eino nechtam? How
do you know the גזר דין of a ציבור tzibbur, not only
can it be torn up but never really gets finally sealed? It
always is left open-ended. So the גמרא Gemara can't accept that. Even
before he gets to quote his פסוק, pasuk, the גמרא Gemara says:
אינו נחתם, eino nechtam, it's not sealed? והכתיב: ve-hachisiv: נכתם עונך לפני,
nechtam avonech lefanai, which has to be a play on words. Your
sin is always stained before me, but presumably there's a play here
of נכתם nechtam and נחתם. nechtam. Okay, but that was the פסוק
pasuk quoted earlier where it says no matter how much soap you
use, the stain will always remain, which sounds like there's an idea
of it being a seal. So the גמרא Gemara, says: אלא אף
על גב שנחתם נקרע. ela af al gav she-nechtam nikra. How do
you know even after it is sealed that it will be torn
up? שנאמר: shene'emar כה' אלוהינו בכל קראנו אליו. ka-Hashem Elokeinu be-chol koreinu
eilav. Like Hashem our God whenever we call out to Him, He
will respond to us, even after the גזר דין. So and that's
a ציבור tzibbur, by the way, בכל קראנו, be-chol koreinu, when we
as a people call out to Him. והכתיב, ve-hachisiv, one minute, but
doesn't the verse say: דרשו ה' בהמצאו? dirshu Hashem be-himmatz'o? Seek out
God when He will be found, not at all times, only when
God is. By the יחיד yachid, only בהימצאו. behimatzo. So the גמרא
Gemara. says ביחיד אימת, beyachid eimat, and when is this time by
the יחיד, yachid when is God available? אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar
Rabbah bar Avuha, אלו עשרה ימים שבין ראש השנה ליום הכיפורים. elu
asarah yamim shebein Rosh Hashanah leYom HaKippurim. These are the עשרת ימי
תשובה, Aseret Yemei Teshuvah, the days between ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. That's when God is particularly responsive. By the
way, we should point out that there are not 10 days between
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. There are seven or eight,
depending on if you have one or two days of ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah But okay inclusive, including ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום
כיפור. Yes, we also read that on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. דרשו
השם בהימצאו. Dirshu Hashem behimatzo. Correct. That is correct. You know, and
the interesting thing here though is that it's understanding that this also
allows for the tearing up of a גזר דין. So whenever this
בהימצאו behimatzo is, again we have the possibility that even for a
יחיד yachid? you can have the tearing up of a גזר דין,
if it's at the right time. And now we'll just have another
statement about the עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. ויהי כעשרת הימים,
Vayehi ke'aseret hayamim, it was after ten days, ויגוף השם את נבל,
vayigof Hashem et Naval, and God smote נבל. Naval. י' ימי מאי
עבידתייהו, Yud yemei mai avidtaihu, why did God wait ten days? אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, כנגד עשרה לגימות
שנתן נבל לעבדי דוד, keneged asara legimot shenatan Naval leavdei David, because
when דוד David sent his messengers and his servants to him, he
gave them food. So actually רש"י Rashi says they weren't ten separate
times, but it says in the פסוקים psukim that דוד David sent
ten people and he served them all one meal. So that's ten
separate ten meals he gave them all at the same time. But
okay. So anyway because of that, that God gave him a ten-day
reprieve. So that's one answer. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה,
Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, no, אלו עשרה ימים שבין
ראש השנה ליום הכיפורים.
elu asarah yamim shebein
Rosh Hashanah leYom HaKippurim. God gave נבל Naval ten days to do
תשובה and only afterwards did he bring this punishment on. So anyway
what we see from all of this is, just to put it
all in context, right? It goes back to the whole משנה Mishnah.
about the idea of when is the דין for the fruit and
the rain etc., is it תחילת דין, techilat din, סוף דין, sof
din, particularly on the רגלים? regalim? Then the issue of the human
being which is on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. And
then we led to a much larger discussion here about this idea
of גזר דין and whether גזר דין can ever be reversed afterwards.
Can it be reversed for a ציבור, tzibur can it be reversed
for a יחיד? yachid, Maybe debates about יחיד, yes by a ציבור,
then issues even with a גזר דין שיש עמו שבועה Gzar Din
sheyesh imo shvuah etc. Okay, and also to remind you what we
did, I mean very central to the גמרא, Gemara this whole thing
about when these דינים dinim take place. The idea of דין שלושה
ספרים נפתחים, din sheloshah sefarim niftachim, the three books: רשעים, צדיקים, and
בינוניים, beinoniyim, also wasn't in our משנה. Mishnah On the one hand
that idea of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
And also that idea of באחרית הימים, be'acharit hayamim, you know, in
some messianic times when there will finally be a resurrection and everybody
will be judged, and all the people that will go to גיהינום
Gehennom and through a period in גיהינום Gehennom will ultimately merit the
world to come, and people that will completely be destroyed in גיהינום.
Gehennom. So a lot of sort of eschatology and final judgment, you
know, these are some of the really core discussions around those issues.
Now we end this discussion with going back to our משנה mishna.
and looking specifically about ראש השנה rosh hashana and יום כיפור. Yes,
and is it then only in terms of that sense of seeking
השם Hashem for the community and the individual in between ראש השנה
rosh hashana and יום כיפור? I don't know. In general, it's usually
the דרשו השם בהימצאו Dirshu Hashem behimatzo is understood to be between
ראש השנה rosh hashana and יום כיפור, not so much the fast
days. I mean the fast days are days that we call out
to God but not a day that I think religiously we necessarily
think that God is particularly receptive to our תשובה. I know it's
a little ironic because we're trying to do תשובה, but the idea
of God's receptivity tends to be focused not on the fast days
but on the עשרת ימי תשובה. Aseret Yemei Teshuvah. Okay. Alright, so
let's take a look now at the final point about ראש השנה
rosh hashana and יום כיפור. בראש השנה כל באי עולם עוברים לפניו
כבני מרון. BeRosh Hashanah kol ba'ei olam overin lefanav kivnei maron. On
ראש השנה rosh hashana. all those that enter in the world, presumably
all mankind humankind, pass before God like בני מרון. bnei maron. מאי
כבני מרון? Mai kivnei maron? What are בני מרון? bnei maron? הכא
תרגימו כבני אמרנא. Hacha targuimu kivnei amrana. Here in בבל Bavel we
translate it as בני אמרנא. bnei amrana. What does that mean? So
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says, כבני אמרנא, kivnei
amrana, about ten lines from the top, fifteen lines from the top,
ככבשים שמונין אותם לעשרן, kekvasim shemonin otam le'asran, like lambs, sheep that
you count when you take מעשר, ma'aser, ויוצאין זה אחר זה בפתח
קטן שאין יכולין לצאת כאחד. veyotzin zeh achar zeh befetach katan she'ein
yecholin latzet k'echad. Like we've been talking about מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behema,
so it's lambs that are walking, sheep that are walking single file
and that they're being counted. I'm going to read the three explanations
and then I'm going to talk about the symbolism. ריש לקיש אמר
כמעלות בית מרון, Reish Lakish amar kema'alot Beit Maron, like the ascents
in בית מרון. Beit Maron. What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi
again says, הדרך קצר ואין שנים יכולים לילך זה בצד זה שהעמק
עמוק משני צידי הדרך. haderech katzar ve'ein shenayim yecholim leilech zeh betzad
zeh sheha'emek amok mishenei tziddei haderech. Okay, so basically what you've got
is, you've got like you know... Like one of those mountain passes,
right? I once had, you know, you got like, I don’t know,
you know those roads on those mountain passes, right? And here’s the
valley below. Okay. So that’s you’re going up the מעלות בני מרון,
maalot Bnei Maron, very narrow, one by one, and there’s this huge
valley below. Okay. That’s כמעלות בני מרון. k’maalot Bnei Maron. Where were
we? And רבה בר בר חנה אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rabbah
bar bar Chana amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel כחיילות של בית דוד.
k’chayalot shel Beit David. No, like the soldiers of בית דוד. Beit
David. רש"י Rashi says that the language is לשון מרות ואדנות. lashon
marut v’adnut. Somehow מרון Maron means like a master, but anyway like
soldiers walking in single file. Now right, so exactly. So the imagery
here I think is very powerful and three different imageries of what
it means to be standing in דין on ראש השנה ויום כיפור.
Rosh Hashanah v’Yom Kippur. This is I think the scariest one, right?
This is you’re all walking like on that narrow precipice, right? A
little slip and then you go down into the valley below. So
this is the one that really sort of has that sense about
hanging by a thread and the precariousness of your life hanging in
judgment. The idea of sheep?
Maybe it’s less personal?
No, I don’t know. You could say that, but who counts the
sheep is the shepherd. I sort of see the one about the
sheep as very much about sort of God as the caring, nurturing
shepherd. We are the innocent
sheep, we’re helpless, but we give over
our trust into God, so we acknowledge our helplessness but we also
believe that God is the shepherd that is tending to us and
caring for us. כחיילות בית דוד k’chayalot Beit David is what?
More intense? It’s just random.
Well רש"י Rashi has the idea of counting every tenth one. That’s
not in the גמרא. gemara The גמרא Gemara just says the sheep.
I don’t know, I wouldn’t underscore that. But the כחיילות בית דוד
k’chayalot Beit David I would say is very powerful as sort of
to think about a sense of pride.
Like if we’ve done תשובה and we’ve worked at
it and we understand what our responsibilities are and we’re ready to
stand for, what is it the soldier stands for? Not the inspection.
Here we are, we’re ready for inspection. We’ve shined our shoes and
everything’s in place and we’re standing for inspection. It’s a very different
type of an imagery of how we think of ourselves approaching it.
Seth, you wanted to say something before? I’d say the shepherd and
flock finds its way into the liturgy. Oh כבקרת רועה עדרו, k’vakarat
ro’eh edro, right. כן תעביר ותספור ותמנה, ken ta’avir v’tispor v’timneh, right.
But you’re right, but then it also has that sense of you
don’t know which one is going to survive, right? מי יחיה ומי
ימות, mi yichyeh u’mi yamut, right. So that’s true. I was trying
to maybe make it a little bit more about the shepherd tending
to the flock. I think so, I think that’s still there. Yes,
what do you? Both ArtScroll and Steinsaltz suggest that ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish may be referring specifically to הר מרון Har Meron in Northern
Israel. Okay. That has a very steep and dangerous path up. Ah,
okay, good. But I think כבני מרון k’vnei Maron this idea that
it means soldiers... does he say something in Steinsaltz? I think I
remember that there was some etymology about that, about בני מרון Bnei
Maron meaning soldiers, no? The Jewish people are the army of הקדוש
ברוך הוא in constant battle with their יצר הרע. yetzer hara. Oh,
okay. That wasn’t exactly what I was thinking. But anyway, but no,
but doesn’t he say something about the word בני מרון Bnei Maron
meaning? מרות? marut? Yes, Rav Yehuda? What he says about... he says
מרות... marut... yeah, that’s what רש"י Rashi says. Yeah, רש"י Rashi says
that. But I thought there was some other etymology of בני מרון
Bnei Maron meaning some maybe Latin root or something. All right, anyway,
moving on. Anyway, very powerful different imageries about the דין on ראש
השנה. rosh hashana I think Alter takes it as one word and
it’s כבנומרון. k’vnumaron. I think there’s some word like כבנומרון, k’vnumaron, not
בני מרון. Bnei Maron. Like an enumerated number? Something like that, yes.
See what the Hebrew Steinsaltz has. I do remember that there’s some
Greek etymology here. Okay, so אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי
יוחנן וכולן נסקרים בסקירה אחת. amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi
Yochanan v’chulan niskarin b’skira achat. Even though they are judged one by
one, all of these also have an idea of single file, nevertheless
God looks at all of them in one moment. In one glance
God looks at everyone and judges everyone individually. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק אף אנן נמי תנינא. amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak af anan
nami tanina. That’s implicit in our משנה. mishna Because the משנה mishna.
ended with the פסוק pasuk of היוצר יחד לבם המבין אל כל
מעשיהם. hayotzer yachad libam hamevin el kol ma’aseihem. He fashions their heart
as one and understands all their deeds. So מאי קאמר? mai ka’amar?
What does the verse mean? אילימא הכי קאמר, eileima hachi ka’amar, this
is what it means: דברינהו לכולי עלמא מיחד לביהו כהדדי. d’varinhu l’chulei
alma meyachad libaihu k’hadadi. God takes the whole world and unites their
hearts as one, meaning היוצר יחד לבם, hayotzer yachad libam, he fashions
their heart as one. One. He takes everybody's heart and makes it
all as one, like creates unity. והא חזינן דלאו הכי הוא, ve'ha
chazinan de'lav hachi hu, it's not true, we're not a unified world.
אלא, that's not what the פסוק pasuk means; it's not that God
fashions together our hearts. אלא לאו הכי קאמר, ella lav hachi ka'amar,
this is how you read the verse: היוצר, hayotzer, the creator, יחד
לבם, yachad libam, רואה יחד לבם, ro'eh yachad libam, sees everybody's heart
as one, ומבין אל כל מעשיהם umevin el kol ma'aseihem and understands
all their deeds. So God sees us all at the same time
even though he's seeing us all individually. Okay. So that's the idea
that we're all judged individually and we're also all judged at once.
Okay, so what does he have here? כבני מרון? kivnei maron? That's
מעלות בני חורין. ma'alot bnei chorin. Oh, בני מרון. bnei maron. מכתבי
יד שונים הגורסים כבנומרון mikitvei yad shonim hagorsim kivenumeron מהשורש המילה מן
mehameshoresh hamila min numerus, הלאטינית, halatinit, the Latin word numerus, על דרך
השאלה מיוונית al derech hash'ala miyevanit from the Greek word נומרון, numeron,
which means אנשי צבא. anshei tza'va. Right, a soldier. וכן מצוי בביטוי
דומה ביוונית שאנשים עומדים כמו בנומרון. vechen matzui bevitu'i domeh biyevanit she'anashim
omdim k'mo benumeron. In Greek there is a phrase, people standing as
if as in a numeron. ואלו מציינים איפוא פירושו של רב יהודה.
ve'elu metzayanim eifo perusho shel rav yehuda. So exactly that phrase, not
just that the word numeron means soldiers, but to stand as a
soldier is a Greek phrase. So that almost definitely the original פשט
pshat of that. Okay, thank you. על ששה דברים al shisha devarim
next משנה. mishna על ששה דברים השלוחים יוצאים. al shisha devarim hashuluchim
yotzim. So now we have four ראש השנהs. rosh hashana I'm sorry,
ששה חדשים. shisha chadashim. We have four ראש השנהs, rosh hashana we
have four times people are judged, four periods of judgment, six times,
ששה ראשי חדשים shisha rashei chadashim that the שלוחים shuluchim go out
to tell people when the ראש חודש rosh chodesh was established. על
ניסן מפני הפסח, al nisan mipnei hapesach, on Nisan to tell people
when ראש חודש ניסן rosh chodesh nisan is so they should know
when to celebrate פסח. pesach. על אב מפני התענית, al av mipnei
hata'anit, on Av so they should know when it's תשעה באב. tisha
be'av. When are they going out? They are going out right after
בית דין beit din was מקדש החודש. mekadesh hachodesh. Now is this
the time of בית המקדש? beit hamikdash? So presumably it is, no,
presumably it's after חורבן הבית. churban habayit. So your question is what
does מפני הפסח mipnei hapesach mean? But פסח pesach means חג המצות.
chag hamatzot. Presumably פסח pesach means חג המצות, chag hamatzot, doesn't mean
the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. But that's a good question. There is
some discussion about there's definitely evidence that after חורבן הבית churban habayit
people were still bringing פסח pesach or pseudo-פסח. pesach. Maybe a פסח
pesach on הר הבית, har habayit, a pseudo-פסח pesach off of הר
הבית. har habayit. So some people want to say that ניסן מפני
הפסח nisan mipnei hapesach means for those people that were still bringing
a type of a קרבן פסח. korban pesach. I find that a
very hard to believe reason because even if there were some people
doing it, that the central בית דין beit din would be sending
out שלוחים—I shuluchim mean, yes, even if we say that the strong
opposition to that came later and it was somewhat tolerated or somewhat
even accepted, but that they would send out שלוחים shuluchim for that,
that's not a ציבור need. I find that hard to believe. פסח
pesach presumably here just means חג המצות, chag hamatzot, what we call
פסח, pesach, which already in the משנה mishna, is called פסח. pesach.
I mean, it's already in the earlier משנה, right? It's בפסח על
התבואה, bepesach al hatvu'ah, פסח pesach means חג המצות, chag hamatzot, does
not mean the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Was this then during בר
כוכבא bar kochva when we got back control of ירושלים yerushalayim for
a few years? Maybe. I mean, they would still do קידוש החודש.
kidush hachodesh. Oh, you mean potentially the time of בר כוכבא? bar
kochva? Yeah, yeah. But they would do קידוש החודש kidush hachodesh even
after חורבן הבית. churban habayit. This is presumably after חורבן הבית. churban
habayit. So on ניסן nisan to tell people when they were מקדש
החודש mekadesh hachodesh so that they could celebrate פסח pesach at the
right time. על אב מפני התענית, al av mipnei hata'anit, on Av
for תשעה באב. tisha be'av.
על אלול מפני ראש השנה, al elul mipnei rosh hashana, on Elul
for ראש השנה rosh hashana because you can't send them out on
ראש השנה to
tell people when to celebrate ראש השנה. So people have to assume,
since almost all years אלול elul was only 29 days, so if
you know when ראש חודש אלול rosh chodesh elul is and you
assume 29 days, you can figure out when ראש השנה is. על
תשרי מפני תקנת המועדות, al tishrei mipnei takanat hamo'adot, then after ראש
השנה they would send out the שלוחים shuluchim to tell them when
תשרי tishrei was established so that they could correct in case
it was wrong, in
case אלול elul
wasn't 29 days, or to reaffirm
that people made sure that they—yes, you were right, that is when
ראש השנה was. So they sent them out after ראש השנה to
tell them about ראש חודש תשרי rosh chodesh tishrei just to be
safe. על כסלו מפני חנוכה, al kislev mipnei chanuka, on Kislev they
sent them out for חנוכה. chanuka. That's when they had the longest
time to get to people. ועל אדר מפני פורים, ve'al adar mipnei
purim, and on Adar they sent them out to know when to
celebrate פורים. purim. And obviously they didn't have to send out people
for שבועות shavuot because you figure it out based on פסח. pesach.
Okay? וכשהיה בית המקדש קיים, veche'shehaya beit hamikdash kayam, and here's the
evidence that we're talking after חורבן, churban, when there was a בית
המקדש, beit hamikdash, יוצאים אף על אייר מפני פסח קטן. yotzim af
al iyar mipnei pesach katan. They go out even on אייר iyar
to tell people when to bring the פסח שני. pesach sheni. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says ולפוק נמי אטבת ותמוז? ve'lifok nami
ateivet vetamuz? Why not if you're going out for תשעה באב, tisha
be'av, go out for תמוז tamuz and טבת teivet for שבעה עשר
בתמוז shiva asar betamuz ועשרה בטבת? va'asarah beteivet? Your people have to
know when to do the fast. So obviously the obvious reason is
that you can only send out שלוחים shuluchim so many times, so
maybe the minor fasts didn't warrant it as much, which is... Essentially
what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. Let's take a look. דאמר
רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא: de-amar Rav Chana bar
Bizna amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida: מאי דכתיב? mai d'ksiv? What's meant by
the verse? כה אמר ה' צבאות: ko amar Hashem Tzevaos: צום הרביעי
וצום החמישי וצום השביעי וצום העשירי יהיה לבית יהודה לששון ולשמחה. tzom
ha-revi'i ve-tzom ha-chamishi ve-tzom ha-shvi'i ve-tzom ha-asiri yihiyeh le-veis Yehudah le-sason u-le-simcha.
So says the Lord of Hosts, right this is when they came
back in the time of the second בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and
they were asking זכריה Zecharya should we continue to fast as we
have fasted until now? And the prophecy was no, those things that
had been fasts they will become days of rejoicing now that we're
having a rebuilding of the temple. So what are those dates? So
the four, well the גמרא Gemara will say. So these are basically
all of our fasts, we'll see how the גמרא Gemara unpacks that
in a minute. קרי ליה צום וקרי ליה ששון ושמחה. kari lei
tzom ve-kari lei sason ve-simcha. It calls it both a fast and
it calls it rejoicing. It's funny that the גמרא Gemara makes this
like it's a problem, the פסוקים psukim are explicit that one is
transforming into the other, which is what the גמרא Gemara says. בזמן
שיש שלום, bizman she-yesh shalom, when there's peace meaning it's good times,
certainly time that there's a בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, we'll see how
שלום shalom is explained, יהיו לששון ולשמחה, yihyu le-sason u-le-simcha, those days
transform into days of rejoicing. אין שלום, ein shalom, if there's no
peace, צום, tzom, it's a fast day. So you see you have
all these fast days. So if you have all these fast days,
right, שבעה בתמוז, Shiva B'Tammuz, עשרה בטבת, Asara B'Teves, etc., why aren't
and that's when there's a חורבן הבית, churban ha-bayis, why aren't the
שלוחים shluchim going out for the fast days? So אמר רב פפא
הכי קאמר. amar Rav Pappa hachi ka'amar. No, here's how you have
to read it. בזמן שיש שלום, bizman she-yesh shalom, when there's true
peace, it's like a time of a בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, יהיו
לששון ולשמחה. yihyu le-sason u-le-simcha. It's a time of rejoicing. יש גזירת
המלכות, yesh gzeiras ha-malchus, if it's the opposite extreme, there's the edict
from the government, meaning like we're under oppression, at a time of
oppression, צום, tzom, then they're fast days. אין גזירת המלכות, ein gzeiras
ha-malchus, if it's like a time where on the one hand it's
not a perfect time, there's no בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, on the
other hand we're not being actively oppressed, in those types of times,
אין שלום, ein shalom, there's not it's not גזירת מלכות gzeiras malchus
but it's also not שלום, shalom, then רצו מתענים רצו אין מתענים.
ratzu mis'anim ratzu ein mis'anim. If you want to you fast, if
you want to you don't fast. So you don't have to fast
on the minor fast days when it's not a period of oppression.
And by the way, you know, I still you know Briskers who
tend to be מחמיר machmir on everything, crazy חומרות, chumros, apparently they
have a tradition, I don't know if this is true about all
of them, but the ones I knew, that they basically don't fast
on the minor fast days. So I was like once I was
like shocked and I was like, you know, saying something like what?
Are you a חולה, choleh, is it hard for you to fast,
does it give you a headache? Because you know the threshold is
a lot less on these minor fasts. No, I don't want to.
רצו אין מתענים. ratzu ein mis'anim. It gets in the way of
my תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. So anyway, again I can't promise that
that's how all of them act, but it is pretty interesting that
in principle that's the הלכה halacha of רצו אין מתענים, ratzu ein
mis'anim, but you go try to find that in the שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, you know, the threshold is lower in terms of like
headaches and whatever, but nevertheless that's pretty we have somewhat bracketed that
הלכה. halacha. So the גמרא Gemara. says yes but it's the community
as a whole, it's not an individual choice, the community as a
whole has to רצו אין מתענים. ratzu ein mis'anim. Yeah, yeah, I
know, yeah, let's go see if we do that in our entire
community make that choice see how how happy people are with that.
Anyway, but okay, I figured anyway people would say something like it's
sort of like מעריב, Ma'ariv, you know, מעריב Ma'ariv is רשות, reshus,
but now we've all decided to do it. Okay, אי הכי ei
hachi says the anyway that's why they don't go out, because you
know, it's you don't have to do it. אי הכי תשעה באב
נמי? ei hachi Tisha B'Av nami? If that's true don't go out
for תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, that's also one of the fast days
listed here. No. אמר רב פפא שאני תשעה באב הואיל והוכפלו בו
צרות. amar Rav Pappa shani Tisha B'Av ho'il ve-huchplu bo tzaros. No,
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is special. There were so many, you know,
tragedies that befell us on תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, that is not
an optional fast day. דאמר מר בתשעה באב חרב הבית בראשונה ובשניה,
de-amar Mar be-Tisha B'Av charav ha-bayis be-rishona u-ve-shniya, the בית המקדש Beis
ha-Mikdash was destroyed the first time and the second time, ונלכדה ביתר,
ve-nilkeda Beitar, Beitar was destroyed, ונחרשה העיר, ve-nechrasha ha-ir, the city was
plowed over. So and תוספות Tosafos points out that you know the
גמרא it also says in תענית Taanis that there were many things
that happened in on שבעה עשר בתמוז, Shivah Asar B'Tammuz, but תוספות
Tosafos says but yes but the repetition, first of all the weight
of what happened, the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash was destroyed but also
the same thing twice, it wasn't like five different random things. Okay,
obviously תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is much weightier, also you know תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av starts the night before, whereas these other fast days
do not, although when we learn תענית Taanis we'll see some issues
around how obvious all of those differences are. But clearly תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av has a special status. Okay, תניא tanya we taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, now we're going to look at unpacking this פסוק
pasuk that lists the different fast days. It's interesting though it's not
that the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash was destroyed is itself enough, it's
the double, the double, right, right. It is true you would have
said that just the fact that it's the day of the חורבן
הבית churban ha-bayis is itself the point. אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabbi
Shimon, right, that's true. אמר רבי שמעון ארבעה דברים היה רבי עקיבא
דורש ורבי שמעון, amar Rabbi Shimon arba'ah devarim hayah Rabbi Akiva doresh
ve-Rabbi Shimon, Rabbi Shimon said four things Rabbi Akiva used to explicate
ואני אין דורש כמותו ve-ani ein doresh kemoso and I don't agree
with his interpretation. Okay and now we're going to look at one
of them. The other three, you know, you could go look at
the תוספתא, Tosefta, we're going to look at one of them. צום
הרביעי, tzom ha-revi'i, so this is the this is how Rabbi Akiva
explains it. זה שבעה עשר בתמוז, zeh shivah asar b'Tammuz, right? ניסן
אייר סיון תמוז. Nisan, Iyar, Sivan, Tammuz. The obviously the the number.
The obviously the numbers here are counting the month.
So he says the ninth of תמוז. Tammuz. Now we would say,
we would say שבעה עשר בתמוז, Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz, okay, because the
first בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, this שבו הובקעה עיר, shebo hufke'ah ir,
that's when the city was breached, שנאמר shene'emar בתשעה לחודש ויחזק הרעב
בעיר ולא היה לחם לעם הארץ, b'tishah lachodesh vayechazak hara'av ba'ir v'lo
hayah lechem l'am ha'aretz, it was in the ninth of the month
and the famine was great and there was no bread ותבקע העיר
vatibaka ha'ir and the city was breached. Now, now תוספות Tosfos says,
if you look at תוספות Tosfos that תשעה בתמוז, Tisha B'Tammuz, תוספות
Tosfos says היינו בראשונה, hainu barishonah, the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
it was breached on the ninth, אבל בשניה הובקעה בי"ז, aval bashniyah
hufke'ah b'yod zayin, ומשום הכי עבדינן בי"ז תענית. umishum hachi avidna b'yod
zayin ta'anis. We do it on the 17th because that was the
second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But then he quotes a fascinating ירושלמי.
Yerushalmi. He says והא ברייתא מסניתין בירושלמי וגרסינן בה בי"ז בתמוז. v'hach
b'raisah masnisin b'yerushalmi v'garsinan bah b'yod zayin b'tammuz. And the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi's
גרסא girsa is the 17th of תמוז Tammuz even in the first
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ואף על גב דכתיב בקרא בתשעה לחודש קלקול
חשבונות היו שם. v'af al gav d'chsiv b'kra b'tisha lachodesh kilkul cheshbonos
hayu sham. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, this is amazing, the verse
says the city was breached on the ninth, it was really the
17th, but there was so much צרות tzaros that they got the
date wrong, okay, in the פסוק. pasuk. ואף על גב דכתיב בקרא
v'af al
gav
d'chsiv b'kra ופליגא אשינוי דדן רצו לומר דמתוך טרדתם טעו בחשבונם. v'pliga
ashitey d'dan rotzu lomar d'mitoch tirdasam ta'u b'cheshbonam. The people at the
time thought
it was the 17th, thought it was the ninth, excuse me, it
was actually the 17th. ולא רצה הפסוק לשנות מכמו שהיו סבורים. v'lo
ratza hapasuk leshanos mikmo shehayu sevorim. Since the people thought it was
the ninth even though it was really the 17th, the פסוק pasuk
said the ninth even though it was really the 17th. Pretty shocking.
Anyway, here it says the ninth. We do it the 17th either
because that was
the original date but they got it wrong,
or because the more standard explanation is the second בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash this
happened on the 17th. Okay,
so the city was breached, so that's
ninth or שבעה עשר בתמוז. Shiv'ah Asar B'Tammuz. That's צום הרביעי. Tzom
Harevi'i. צום החמישי, Tzom Hachamishi, last narrow line, זה תשעה באב, zeh
Tisha B'Av, שבו נשרף בית אלקינו, shebo nisraf beis elokeinu, that's where
the house of our God was burnt.
ואמאי קרי ליה חמישי?
v'amai
karei lei chamishi?
What does חמישי hamishi mean? חמישי לחודשים, chamishi lachadashim, the fifth month.
Okay, I'm sorry, did I skip the line before? Before it said
ואמאי קרי ליה רביעי? v'amai karei lei revi'i? רביעי לחודשים. revi'i lachadashim.
Fine. תמוז Tammuz is the fourth of the month, five is the
fifth of the month, it's אב. Av. צום השביעי, Tzom Hashvi'i, the
seventh month, זה ג' בתשרי, zeh gimel b'tishrei, שבו נהרג גדליה בן
אחיקם. shebo neherag Gedalyah ben Achikam. That's the third of תשרי Tishrei
when גדליה בן אחיקם, Gedalyah ben Achikam, the governor who was left
behind was murdered by in this whole plot. ומי הרגו? umi harago?
Who killed him? ישמעאל בן נתניה הרגו. Yishmael ben Nesanyah harago. ללמדך
ששקולה מיתתן של צדיקים כשריפת בית אלקינו. l'lamedcha sheshkulah misasan shel tzadikkim
k'sreifeis beis elokeinu. It's right there in the list. It's given equal
weight to תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, so the killing of the righteous,
funny that גדליה Gedalyah is a righteous, anyway is as important as,
I mean, who'd want to accept לשון הרע lashon hara anyway, is
has you know is as weighty as the burning of our temple.
ואמאי קרי ליה שביעי? v'amai karei lei shvi'i? Why is it called
the seventh? שביעי לחודשים, shvi'i lachadashim, the seventh month counting from ניסן.
Nissan. תשרי Tishrei is the seventh month. צום העשירי, Tzom Ha'asiri, the
10th month, זה עשרה בטבת, zeh asarah b'teves, the 10th of טבת,
Teves, שבו סמך מלך בבל על ירושלים. shebo samach melech bavel al
yerushalayim. That's when the king of בבל Bavel laid siege to Jerusalem,
which happened obviously chronologically before all these other events, שנאמר ויהי דבר
ה' אלי בשנה התשיעית בחודש העשירי בעשור לחודש. vay'hi d'var Hashem elai
bashanah tishis bachodesh ha'asiri b'asor lachodesh. On the 10th month, בעשור לחודש
b'asor lachodesh on the 10th of the month, again counting from ניסן,
Nissan, that's עשרה בטבת. asarah b'teves. לאמר בן אדם כתוב לך את
שם היום הזה את עצם היום הזה. lemor ben adam ksov lecha
es shem hayom hazeh et esem hayom hazeh. Write the very write
this day in the middle of this day. סמך את עצם היום
הזה, samach et esem hayom hazeh, סמך מלך בבל על ירושלים. samach
melech bavel al yerushalayim. At the very essence of this day, write
down this date, you will see that this is the day when
the king of Babylon sit laid siege to Jerusalem. מאי סמך? mai
samach? What's laid siege? סמך. samach. He drew close to, but it
means he surrounded the city, okay, he approached the city is literally
what it means. ואמאי קרי ליה עשירי? v'amai karei lei asiri? Why
is it called the 10th? עשירי לחודשים, asiri lachadashim, the 10th of
the month. Okay, so that's what we have, the fasts as we
know them. והלא, v'halo, next and we've just got one question, עשירי
לחודשים. asiri lachadashim. והלא היה ראוי זה לכתוב ראשון, v'halo hayah ra'uy
zeh lichtov rishon, that should have been first because that chronologically the
laying siege happened before all the rest. ולמה נכתב כאן? v'lamah nichtav
kan? Why was it written here? כדי להסדיר חודשים כתיקנן, k'dei l'hasdir
chadashim k'tiknan, in order to have the months go in order, right?
Because you have, right, רביעי, revi'i, חמישי, hamishi, חמישי, hamishi, whatever, I
mean what's the next one? צום רביעי, צום החמישי, וצום השביעי, וצום
העשירי. tzom revi'i, tzom hachamishi, v'tzom hashvi'i, v'tzom ha'asiri. Right? So this
is תמוז, Tammuz, אב, Av, תשרי, Tishrei, and טבת. Teves. Right? So
and this is, right so and then this is, so this is
the breaching of the city, חורבן הבית, Churban Habayis, גדליה, Gedalyah, so
all of that is chronological order, right? The city was breached, the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, they were sent into גלות. galus.
Right? There was a contingent left behind that גדליה Gedalyah was put
in charge of, right, and then he was assassinated. But then we
have עשרה בטבת asarah b'teves which is סמך מלך בבל, samach melech
bavel, right, so which is chronologically happened obviously before the breaching. So
that's what he says, this should have been mentioned first, but we
had it this way in order to list all the months in
order. order. Okay, so back to the גמרא. That's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. ולמה נכתב כאן כדי להסמיך חודשים כתיקנן? Velama nichtav kan kidei
lehasmich chadashim k'tiknan? ואני, Va'ani, and I, איני אומר כן, eini omer
kein, I don't say that. אלא צום העשירי זה חמישה בטבת. Ella
tzom ha'asiri zeh chamishah b'Tevet. וצום העשירי Vetzom ha'asiri is not עשרה
בטבת, Asara b'Tevet, which chronologically happened much earlier. It's the fifth of
Tevet. What happened on the fifth of Tevet? שבו באה שמועה לגולה
שהוכתה העיר. Shebo ba'ah shemuah lagolah shehukta ha'ir. That's when the report
came to the exile, the people that had been exiled before חורבן
הבית. Churban haBayit. Right, there was a whole major section of the
community that had already been sent in exile, like 11, 12 years
before חורבן הבית. Churban haBayit. That's when they heard of the חורבן
הבית, Churban haBayit, שנאמר ויהי בשתים עשרה שנה בעשירי בחמישה לחודש, shene'emar
vayehi b'shteim esre shanah b'asiri b'chamishah lachodesh, on the fifth of Tevet,
לגלותנו, legalutenu, of our exile, בא אלי הפליט מירושלים לאמור. ba elai
hapalit miYerushalayim leimor. It was the twelfth year of the exile of
that contingent that had been exiled earlier, twelve years earlier, excuse me,
בא אלי הפליט מירושלים לאמור, ba elai hapalit miYerushalayim leimor, the refugee
came from Jerusalem to say, הוכתה העיר, hukta ha'ir, that the city
has been destroyed. So that was when the report came to the
exile. ועשו יום שמועה כיום שריפה. Va'asu yom shemuah k'yom sereifah. And
the day of the report was as bad, you know, we have
some of these ideas like אבילות aveilut when you hear about a
death, even after the fact, it's sort of like, you know, then
that becomes like the יום קבורה. yom kevurah. So the day of
hearing of that was like the day in which the Temple was
destroyed. That's when it was experienced by the exile, and that's what
I say, he says. So he says this is not סמך מלך
בבל. samach melech Bavel. This is the report reached בבל. Bavel. שמועה
רעה Shemuah ra'ah reached the גלות. galut. And then it is also
in exact chronological order. It was breached, it was destroyed, גדליה Gedalyah
was assassinated, and finally they heard about all the events in גלות.
galut. Where is it? נראין דבריי מדבריו. Nirin devarai midvarav. My approach
appears more correct than his. שאני אומר ראשון ראשון ואחרון אחרון. She'ani
omer rishon rishon ve'achron achron. And I've got everything happening in right
chronological order. והוא אומר על ראשון אחרון ועל אחרון ראשון.
Vehu omer al rishon achron ve'al achron rishon. He says about the
first thing last, right, the laying siege is at the end of
the list, and the last thing
is first, but
a later thing in the list appears first.
אלא שהוא מונה לסדר חודשים.
Ella shehu
moneh l'seder chadashim.
But he'll say,
look, it doesn't matter, I'm just listing the months in order. ואני
מונה לסדר פורענות. Va'ani moneh l'seder pur'anut. And I say, in addition
to the months being listed in order, also you actually have the
events listed in order. Okay, and we will pick up with this
tomorrow now that we understand what those various fast days are.